Finding Aid for College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) publications 1871-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) publications 1871-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.
Includes miscellaneous announcements, annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins, calendars, directories, flyers, guidebooks, manuals, newsletters and reports of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts and the Summer Session. Also includes newsletters from the Honors Program and reports of the Commission on Graduation Requirements, the Committee on the Underclass Experience, and Office of Faculty Counselors.
0346 Bimu C22 2
11 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (Donor no. 1665 )
The records are open for research.
Consult the finding aid for College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) Records.
The University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts Publications (11 linear feet) include addresses, annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins or college catalogs, by-laws, calendars, catalogs, directories, ephemera (including flyers, invitations, posters, and programs), manuals, monographs, newsletters, proceedings marking the centennial of the college, questionnaires, regulations, and reports. These publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications and Student Publications. A large percentage of the publications are bulletins and course catalogs of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) and its predecessor, the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts. There is also extensive information on the Honors Program, the Office of Student Academic Affairs, and LS&A Student Government.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Honors Program.; University of Michigan. Commission on Graduation Requirements.; University of Michigan. Committee on the Underclass Experience.; University of Michigan. Pilot Program.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Honors Program.; University of Michigan. Commission on Graduation Requirements.; University of Michigan. Committee on the Underclass Experience.; University of Michigan. Pilot Program.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Literature, Science, and the Arts.
Genre/Form:
Catalogs, College.; Announcements.; Annual reports.; Bibliographies.; Brochures.; Bulletins.; Directories.; Guidebooks.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series (8.4 linear feet) includes addresses, annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins (course catalogs), by-laws, calendars, catalogs, directories, manuals, newsletters, proceedings, programs, regulations, and reports.
  The annual reports cover the period from 1933 to 1998, with the bulk documenting the period from 1977 to 1998. They briefly describe the activities of the college and list donors to the college's programs. (For earlier annual reports the researcher should consult the President's Report (call no. Fimu, B3), published from 1853 to 1984). The brochures describe some of the special offerings of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts including collegiate seminars, first year seminars, special foreign language offerings, general studies, and various theme semesters. These brochures cover the period from the 1980s through 1990.
  The bulletins or college catalogs (2.4 linear feet) describe the admissions requirements, course offerings (but not descriptions), degree requirements, facilities, and history of the college. The print version of the bulletin, from 1871 to the present is the authoritative source of admissions information, course offerings, and degree requirements. Under the heading "catalogs" the researcher will find about 1 linear foot of course descriptions under the titles LSA Course Guide documenting the period from 1976 to 1998, and the LS&A Brief Course Guide covering the period from 2001 to 2002. These titles also contain information about prerequisites.
  In the manuals subseries there are handbooks for first year students, covering the period from 1988 to the present. These volumes include an alphabetical listing, by department, of detailed course descriptions, even noting differences between the various sections offered. Distribution information (Social Sciences, Humanities, etc.), prerequisites, credits, and instructors are also identified. These handbooks also contain information about LS&A degree requirements, a directory of academic advising and counseling services, advice on distribution requirements, selecting an advisor, concentration course information, in addition to book costs, and special fees associated with the course. The are found under various titles such as the:
  Freshman Course Guide, 1988
  First Year Handbook and Freshman Fall Course Guide, 1988-1994
  First Year Handbook, 1994 to the present
  In 1997 the course information was broken out of the First Year Handbook into a separate publication entitled the First Year Course Guide. This publications continues to be published to the present.
  In this subseries researchers will also find handbooks for the faculty, international students, parents, and transfer students. The Handbook for LSA Instructional Staff was compiled in 1981 from the Faculty Code, the governing document created by the LS&A faculty. The Information and Regulations Governing the Conduct of Undergraduate Courses, published in 1962 and 1967, was to provide the teaching staff with a readily accessible list of the policies and procedures governing the conduct of LS&A courses. The International Student Handbook published from 1998 to the present contains information to help ease the transition for incoming, non-American students. There is information on LS&A advising resources, academic resources, learning communities, academic conduct, international student associations, and helpful hints for living far from home for the first time. The Parent Handbook includes similar information with hints for how parents can help their student succeed at the University of Michigan. The library holds this publication from 1997 to 2002. In later years this publication became the LSA Guide for Parents and is available as well in the sub series. The Transfer Student Handbook, dating from 1989 to the present, discusses LS&A advising, but concentrates on the transfer of credits from other academic institutions and planning for the students' academic career at Michigan.
  The LSA Distribution Book, in conjunction with the Bulletin, is designed to help students select courses outside of their concentration area in the categories of Humanities, Natural Science, and Social Sciences. By selecting courses not in their concentration or cognate fields they are broadening their intellectual horizons and interests, which is a goal of a University of Michigan education. The LSA Distribution Book lists various courses, arranged alphabetically by department, with brief descriptions and explains how these courses can be used to fulfill distribution requirements. The library holds this publication from 1989 to 1992.
  The subseries newsletters contains several titles including Diagonalia, LSA Checkpoint, LSA Magazine, and the LSA Student Academic Affairs Newsletter. The Diagonalia, published from 1971 to 1975, provides much information about what was going on in the dean's office and the various departments in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. It describes new courses being offered, programs being developed, and long-range planning. There are also articles by faculty members on topics such as creativity or liberal arts education. The LSA Checkpoint published from 1974 to 1996, and its successor LSA Student Academic Affairs Newsletter issued from 1996 to 1998, were originally published monthly during the academic year and later three to four times a year. These newsletters discuss summer orientation, registration, new courses, mini-courses, graduation and counseling information. The library does not hold a complete run of these publication. The LSA Magazine, dating from 1977 to the present, documents the activities of the various administrators, faculty, staff, students, and alumni of the college. Currently published twice a year, the Bentley Library holds a nearly complete run of this publication.
  There are three small commencement programs, from 1992 through 1994, included in this series. A better source for commencement information, including lists of graduates, will be found in the University of Michigan. Chief Marshall records (call no. 8753, Bimu, E3, 2), documenting the period from 1914 to the present.
  - Addresses
    - Robots and Free Minds: [Six Public Lectures by Arthur W. Burks including 1978 Henry Russel Lecture], 1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - The Dean's Report, 1973 (Box 1)
    - LSA Honor Roll and Report to Alumni, 1977-1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - LSA Report, 1993-1999 (Box 1)
    - President's Report, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Report from the Dean, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - The Report of The College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, 1933-1940 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Books That May Change Your Life, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Collegiate Seminars, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Foreign Languages, 1953-1981 (Box 1)
    - Freshman Seminars, 1978-1990 (Box 1)
    - General Studies, undated (Box 1)
    - Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1957-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1883-2001, undated (Box 1)
    - Shared Discovery, undated (Box 1)
    - Theme Semesters, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Traditions in the Making: Special Programs in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (Course Catalogs)
    - Summer Session, 3 folders
      - 1897-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1923 (Box 1)
      - 1942-1945, 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1871/72-1923/24, 7 folders; 5 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1924/25-1963/64, 20 folders (Box 2)
    - 1964/65-1998/99, 20 folders (Box 3)
    - 1999/2000-2010/2011, 11 folders (Box 4)
    - Course of Instruction in the Science and Art of Teaching, 1880/81 (Box 4)
  - By-Laws
    - By-Laws of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, [ca. 1946] (Box 4)
    - By-Laws of the Department of Science, Literature and the Arts, 1855 (Box 4)
  - Calendars
    - The College of Literature, Science & the Arts, 1997, 1998 (Box 4)
    - LS&A Sampler, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Themes of Undergraduate Life, 1992 (Box 4)
    - The College of Literature, Science & the Arts, 2008, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
  - Catalogs
    - LS&A Brief Course Guide, 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - LSA Course Descriptions, 1978-1979 (Box 5A)
    - LSA Course Guide
      - 1976-1985, 10 folders (Box 5A)
      - 1985-1991, 6 folders (Box 5B)
      - 1991-1998, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Directories
    - List of Advisory Groups, 1912/13 (Box 6)
  - E-Mail Printouts 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Flyers
    - Miscellaneous 1985-2000, undated (Box 6)
    - Theme Semesters (Box 6)
    - Warner-Lambert Lecture 1985-1989, undated (Box 6)
  - Manuals
    - Faculty Code (1977 Revision), 1977 (Box 6)
    - First Year Course Guide, 1997-2007, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - First Year Handbook, 1994-2007, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - First Year Handbook and Freshman Fall Course Guide, 1988/89-1994, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Freshman Course Guide, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Freshman LSA Course Guide, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Handbook for Instructional Staff, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Information and Regulations Governing the Conduct of Undergraduate Courses, 1956 19621967 (Box 7)
    - International Student Handbook, 1998-2004, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - LSA Distribution Book, 1989/90-1992/93, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Parent Handbook (also called Guide for Parents), 1997-2002, 2004-2006, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Policies and Procedures for the Academic Staff, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Pre Health Professions Booklet-Fall 98, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Secretaries' Procedure Manual, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Transfer Student Handbook, 1989/90-2003, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Monographs
    - The World Around the Chinese Artist: Aspect of Realism in Chinese Painting by Richard Edwards, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters
    - Addenda, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
    - Diagonalia, 1971-1975, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - LSA, 1973-1977 (Box 7)
    - LSA Campus Days at Michigan, 1997 (Box 7)
    - LSA Checkpoint
      - 1974-1996 volumes 1-23 [Precedes LSA Student Academic Affairs Newsletter], 23 folders (Box 7)
    - LSA Magazine (Box 8)
      - 1977-2012, 2015 volumes 1-20 and 23, 29 folders (Box 8)
    - LSA Parents Newsletter, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - LSA Student Academic Affairs Newsletter, 1996-1998, 2 folders
      [Supercedes LSA Checkpoint]
    - Undergraduate Education, 1990-1992 (Box 8)
  - Posters
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Theme Semesters (Box 8)
  - Proceedings
    - Centennial Celebration of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts of the University of Michigan 1841-1941, 1943 (Box 8)
  - Programs
    - Alice Freeman Palmer Professorship in History April 2004 (Box 8)
    - Commencement 1992-1994 (Box 8)
    - Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture Series 1987-1988 (Box 8)
    - Faculty Seminars May 2000 (Box 8)
    - Warner G. Rice Humanities Award 1984, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Questionnaires
    - Survey of Student Attitudes and Needs, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Regulations
    - Information and Regulations Governing the Conduct of Undergraduate Courses, 1962 (Box 8)
  - Reports
    - Budget Planning
      - 1987/88-1988/89, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Choice of a Field of Concentration, undated (Box 9)
    - Collected Course Materials from Courses in LS&A Addressing Issues of Diversity, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Evaluation of Faculty Services, 1939, 1941, 1953 (Box 9)
    - Outreach Activities, 1999 (Box 9)
    - Program for Building Area Expansion, June 1965 (Box 9)
    - Report on Grading System, 1912-1913 (Box 9)
    - Tables Based on the Examination Reports for June, 1912 Wherein the Recently Adopted Grading System was Used for the First Time, 1912 (Box 9)
    - Trend of Admission Requirements in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1930 (Box 9)
    - Report of the Committee on Admissions, c.1954 (Box 9)
    - Report on the Fall 1997 Theme Semester, Genders, Bodies, Borders (Box 9)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs, and organizations within the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  The Sub-Unit Publications series (2.4 linear feet) includes publications produced by the Academic Advising Center and the Academic Counseling Office, Committee on the Underclass/ Undergraduate Experience, the Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program, First Year Seminar Program, the Honors Program, and Office of Student Academic Affairs.
  The Academic Advising Center includes proceedings and reports from 1998 to 2001 that discuss and provide information regarding changes and initiatives within the college and the curriculum. In these publications the researcher will find discussions about technology, efforts to engage sophomores, information about specific disciplines from astronomy to romance languages. Researchers will also find manuals for concentration advisors for the period from 1991 to 1994 and for faculty counselors from 1977-1978. The Office of Student Academic Affairs publications include several manuals for academic faculty advisors for the 1990s. There is also a Summer Orientation Handbook published from 1991 to 1997, as well as annual reports for this office issued from 1980 to 1994.
  In the early 1970s there was concern that the University of Michigan was not providing a balanced program for its undergraduates. In 1972 a report from the Committee on the Underclass Experience was issued. In 1990, a report entitled A Michigan Education: The Challenges of Undergraduate Education at the University of Michigan, was published by the Committee on the Undergraduate Experience. This report is included with the other publications of the committee. There are also reports regarding counseling and pedagogy. These reports spurred the development of the Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program (UROP). Included in the publications of this sub-unit are undated brochures and a 1992 directory describing research projects, the faculty supervisors, and the participating students. The First Year Seminar was developed to give first-year students an opportunity to have a small class experience. The First Year Seminar Program catalogs, covering the period from 1994 to the present, list the First Year Seminar courses with a brief description, the faculty member leading the class, credit hours, and day and time the course is offered. They are arranged first by LSA general requirements (Introductory Composition, Race and Ethnicity, Quantitative Reasoning, Humanities, Natural Science, and Social Science) then alphabetically by department or center.
  The Honors Program publications include annual reports from 1958 to 1976. There is a 1989 directory describing research opportunities for undergraduate honors. The Honors Handbook describes the admission process into the Honors Program, thesis policies, academic policies and procedures related to the Honors Program, research programs, and scholarship programs. There is also a series of newsletters entitled Honorabilia covering the period from 1979 to 1993. These newsletters describe new Honors courses, job opportunities for honors students, thesis information, and new faculty.
  - Academic Advising Center
    - Brochures 2000-2001, undated (Box 9)
    - Newsletters
      - LSA Advising Center Newsletter, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
    - Proceedings
      - Proceedings of Academic Advising Summit Meetings, 2000-2001
    - Reports
      - Report of Academic Advising Summit Meetings, 1998, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Academic Advising Office
    - Questionnaires 1993 (Box 9)
  - Academic Counseling Office
    - Manuals
      - Handbook for Concentration Advisors, 1991-1992, 1994 (Box 9)
      - A Handbook for Faculty Counselors, 1977/78 (Box 9)
  - Advisory Committee on Computing
    - Reports
      - Report of the LS&A Advisory Committee on Computing, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills
    - Brochures 1977, undated (Box 9)
  - Commission on Graduation Requirements
    - Reports
      - Report of the Commission on Graduation Requirements, 1974, undated (Box 9)
  - Committee on College Problems
    - Reports
      - A Comparative Study of Research and Teaching Activities and Their Financial Support in Ten Universities, undated (Box 9)
  - Committee on the Deanship
    - Reports
      - Report of the Committee on the Deanship, 1944 (Box 9)
  - Committee on the Underclass Experience
    - Reports
      - Final Report of the Committee on the Underclass Experience, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Committee on the Undergraduate Experience
    - Reports
      - A Michigan Education: The Challenges of Undergraduate Education at the University of Michigan, 1990, 2 volumes (Box 9)
      - Report of the Subcommittee on Counseling 1991 (Box 9)
      - Report of the Subcommittee on Pedagogy 1991 (Box 9)
      - Report Submitted in May 1991 by the LSA Preconcentration Years Subcommittee (Formerly Atheneum Subcommittee), 1991 (Box 9)
  - Development and External Relations
    - Brochures undated (Box 9)
    - Calendars 1994 (Box 9)
    - E-Mail Printouts 2000-2001 (Box 9)
    - Reports
      - Campaign Report, 1995-1997 (Box 9)
  - Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture Series
    - Programs 1984-1988 (Box 9)
  - First Year Seminar Program
    - Brochures undated (Box 9)
    - Catalogs 1993-2006, 2009 (Box 9)
  - Graduation and Distribution Requirements Subcommittee
    - Reports
      - Report of the Graduation and Distribution Requirements Subcommittee, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Honors Program
    - Annual Reports, 1958-1975/76 (Box 10)
    - Brochures undated (Box 10)
    - Directories
      - Guide to Undergraduate Honors Research Opportunities, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Manuals
      - Guide for First Year Students, 1989 (Box 10)
      - The Honors Handbook, 1981/82-1997 (5 editions) (Box 10)
    - Newsletters
      - Forum (alumni newsletter), 1991, 1997, 2000, 2003-2007 (Box 10)
      - Honorabilia: The Honors Newsletter
        - vol. 1-11 1979-1993, 9 folders (Box 10)
      - Honorabilia: The Underclass Honors Newsletter
        - vol. 8-10 1989/90-1991/92, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Honorabilia: The Upperclass Honors Newsletter
        - vol. 1-3 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Press Releases 1957-1963 (Box 10)
    - Reports
      - The Effectiveness of the Honors Program in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1960 (Box 10)
  - Media Services
    - Brochures undated (Box 10)
  - Michigan Learning Communities
    - Campus neighborhoods at the University of Michigan: New Approaches to learning and Living (Box 10)
    - Brochures (Box 10)
    - Living-Learning programs at the University of Michigan Final Report 1996 (Box 10)
    - The University of Michigan Bulletin: Michigan Learning Communities Proposal (Box 10)
    - Students Talk About College: Essays from the Pilot Program (Box 10)
  - Office of Faculty Counselors for Freshman and Sophomores
    - Manuals
      - Counselors' Handbook, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Office of Student Academic Affairs
    - Annual Reports
      - 1980/81-1994/95, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Manuals
      - Academic Integrity in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, 2000 (Box 10)
      - Graduate Student Teaching Assistant Training and development Program, 1994/1995 (Box 10)
      - Handbook for Academic Advisors, 1992, 1996 (Box 10)
      - Handbook for Concentration Advisors, 1994 (Box 11)
      - Handbook for Faculty and Instructional Staff, 1999-2002, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Handbook for Instructional Staff, 1992, 1994, 1998 (Box 11)
      - Information for Graduate Student Instructors, 1998 (Box 11)
      - Reference Manual for Concentration Advising Staff, undated (Box 11)
      - Reference Manual for Departmental/Program Advising Staff, 2000-2002 (Box 11)
      - Summer Orientation Handbook, 1991-1995, 1997, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Newsletters
      - Concentration News, 1991-1995 (Box 11)
    - Reports
      - Status Report, July 1998 (Box 11)
  - Office of the Assistant Dean for Student Academic Affairs
    - Manuals
      - Academic Judiciary Manual of Procedures, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Office of the Associate Dean for Undergraduate Education
    - Newsletters
      - Undergraduate Education
        - volumes 1-2 1990-1992 (Box 11)
  - Office of Underclass Advising
    - Handbook for Academic Advisors (Box 11)
  - Office of Undergraduate Admissions-LSA Concentrations
    - Brochures, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Pilot Program
    - Annual Report 1986/87 (Box 11)
    - Brochures 1967/68-1979/80, undated (Box 11)
    - Bulletins 1983, undated (Box 11)
    - Essays
      - Students Talk About College: Essays from the Pilot Program, 1986 (Box 11)
    - Job Descriptions
      - Resident Fellow 1970 (Box 11)
    - Manuals